<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: IT | Polyglot]]></title>
  <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/categories/it/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-01T11:15:21-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Fussell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advanced Development and Delivery (ADD)]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/add-1/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-24T01:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/add-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been paid to develop and deliver software since about 1980.  That is 35 years of professional experience.
When I started in 1980 there were a lot of 'old timers' who had been around since 1965 or so.  They were 15 years
ahead of me, and even after finishing college, I had less than ten years to their twenty or so.  This was both
intimidating but also very helpful: after college my main programming language was Smalltalk (ParcPlace, Digitalk, etc.),
which included full source to everything.  So the 'masters' would write masterpieces of code, and I would read them.  And then
try to write my own beautiful things leveraging the masterpieces.  I was late to the party, but could learn quickly.</p>

<p>I also have one other unusual advantage: I do startups.  Lots of startups (<a href="http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/">http://SlumsOfPaloAlto.com/</a>).  A total of ten software startups over a period of
a bit more than a decade.  Each of these startups failed for one reason or another, but each one <em>hugely</em> progressed in
how good my development team ran.  Eight, nine, and ten were <em>crazy</em> productive: I would run production servers for the
whole company at the same time that I built out the product.  Alone.  And generally way faster than the product management
team could keep up.  At PeerCase the product team actually asked me to <em>slow down</em> delivery so they could ponder what
they wanted for longer.  I literally went to Disney World during ASH (a medical conference) to prevent myself from
releasing new features I knew they wanted.  I was paid to <em>not work</em> (well, I was contracting at the time, so I stopped the
hourly billing clock, but my project bonus was the same).</p>

<h2>10x Productivity</h2>

<p>Besides doing startups, I also consult for companies.  I try to help them improve their development methods, usually by at least 4x if not 10x.
A lot of times, people don't believe you can improve things to '10x' the productivity of the current team using new
development and delivery techniques.  At one company, the CIO and a number of other executives believed me, but I had to convince
a lot more stakeholders.  So two amigos and I sent me into the trenches.  I started taking projects estimated as two-developers, six-months,
and doing them in one month.  Part time.  That is more than 12x productivity.  Realistically it was likely about 20x the productivity
because the teams tend to miss their estimates (they go over).</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Then for fun, I was sent into the trenches again but this time had to use <em>some</em> of their development methods.  Still way faster,
but back down to 10x or a bit better.  As the trenches became "less mine" and "more theirs" I would slow down more and more.
Eventually everyone tired of each other and the experiments stopped.</p>

<p>Bizarrely, this company that saw the 20x continues to use the slow, unreliable, method of development.  The workers may have
been scared that the company would only need one in ten of them if they changed to a better method.</p>

<h2>Development Stagnation</h2>

<p>Again, I have been doing this for 35 years.  My skill as a developer has improved over that time, and I now view myself as an '8'
where each increase from '0' represents a doubling of business productivity.  So I am 256 times as productive as a '0', and 16 times
as productive as a '4'.  Stephen Wolfram, Bill Joy, and others are above me, but there are not a lot of people up there anymore.</p>

<p>Getting to be a '4' involves understanding how to program.  Getting to a '6' involves understanding business needs.  But getting to an '8'
involved an incredible / revolutionary change to how software is developed and delivered.  For most of my career, getting to an '8'
was not possible.  Or at least the scale had to be different (i.e. add 50% for each number vs. doubling).</p>

<p>The problem was that software development had made <em>absolutely no progress</em> for 40+ years.  "You lie!" people claim.  "We build software very
differently then we used to!" they say.  Yes, <em>some people</em> have made progress.  But it was people doing it wrong for 40+ years.  The
people who did it right (Xerox PARC, MIT's Lisp group, Xerox El Segundo, Tektronics, etc.) were buzzing along happily with a 4-10x speed
of the rest of the industry.</p>

<p>What is this amazing way to build software?  Well, for 40+ years, the best way to write software was to take a working computer and tweak it.
Then clone that. Voila: you have a new capability on all your computers.  Testing is trivial.  Demoing is trivial.  Fixing
is trivial.  Tweak.  Clone.  Repeat.  Smalltalk, Lisp Machines, Xerox Stars, and so on all used this model.  And they were
blazingly fast to develop on.  And to learn how to develop on.</p>

<p>If you wrote software any way different from that, you were just punishing yourself.  Your software would regress because
you touched too much and broke things.  Your software would take too long to write and be buggy because you wrote it
from scratch instead of tweaking something that worked.  Your software would not do what the business wanted because
you spent months writing it instead of hours tweaking something that was close.  Pain... pain... pain...</p>

<p>When I shifted to Java, I dropped to a '6' from an '8' in Smalltalk.  Lots of developers hated leaving Smalltalk
because of that.  But in my case, I cared about the libraries and people who were moving into Java.  It is not
a great language, but it had a lot of potential.  And Smalltalk imploded when Java was released for free.</p>

<h2>Automated Testing</h2>

<p>So I am in this crappy new language, dealing with jars (usually with source), deploying to containers, building out
linux servers in data centers, and trying to make this whole thing scale to millions of users and international
development teams who like to break my code.  It was fun and hell at the same time.  To avoid my going down to a '4'
because other people broke my code, I leveraged XP practices that were entrenched in startup #3 (Evant / Retail Aspect).
This was one of the first full-bore XP companies with Kent Beck and Rob Mee at the helm of the development team.</p>

<p>XP is very much oriented to "Write tests first".  That is stupid.  You need to figure out what you are doing and
writing tests is not a good way to figure out how to do something.  You <em>do it</em> to figure out how to do it.  But
after you <em>do it</em>, you should write tests to make sure the code still does it tomorrow.  Unfortunately, people
usually forget to write tests after, hence the XP maxim.  I lucked out and a whole bunch of tests existed
when I showed up.  I needed to scale the product to be 1-million times bigger and 1-thousands times faster.
And not break any existing test (unless we changed functionality).</p>

<p>That sold me on automated testing.  It made me slower (say a '5') but it protected me from other people breaking
my working code.  Eventually we used Excel for the automated tests, the business people wrote them directly, and
I was back to a '6'.</p>

<h2>Grails and Opinionated Frameworks</h2>

<p>I became an '8' again when I started using <a href="http://grails.org/">http://grails.org/</a>.  The language (Groovy and Annotated Java)
was now approaching Smalltalk if a bit uglier.  And the automated binding to the database, plugin model,
and other great features in Grails made it so I simply didn't have to worry about a lot of stuff.  I
was getting different benefits from Smalltalk, but they netted out.  And I had the same benefit as
Smalltalk in onboarding others: (1) This is the Grails way, (2) This is my 'tweaks' to the Grails way...
now start asking for features and build them.</p>

<h2>Flex and Angular</h2>

<p>On the client side, I had shifted to using Flex very early on for a company called Winster.  It was a bit
bleading edge at the time, but Flex was very powerful and very productive.  It was basically Smalltalk
on the client.  Eventually Flex/Flash became non-viable because of the iPhone issue, but then Angular
jumped in to replace it.  I tried others (e.g. YUI, Sencha, etc.) and they have pros-and-cons, but Angular
is very good and very Flex-like.</p>

<h2>Advanced Development and Delivery (ADD)</h2>

<p>OK, so above describes a lot of the stack I tend to use, but that isn't where the '256x' comes from.  Above I claimed
I was an '8' but that was on the old '50%' or maybe '70%' more scale.  On the new scale, I am a '6' with the stack above
<em>until</em> you add in the ADD: The Advanced Development and Delivery environment.</p>

<p>The ADD came to me incrementally from Evant, through my own failed attempt at productizing it (Velidom), and fully
germinated with my last software startup: Rumble.  "Amusingly", Velidom was killed by two of the four ingredients,
tried to work around problems with SVN that is replaced by one of the four ingredients, and included as part
of the product one of the four ingredients.  If we had just focused on that <em>one ingredient</em> and not the whole
software factory, Velidom would now be owned by Atlassian.</p>

<p>The four ingredients are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Amazon EC2 <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/">http://aws.amazon.com/</a></li>
<li>Amazon S3  <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/">http://aws.amazon.com/</a></li>
<li>GitHub.com <a href="http://github.com/">http://github.com/</a></li>
<li>HipChat    <a href="http://HipChat.com/">http://HipChat.com/</a></li>
</ul>


<p>These four ingredients, when baked properly together, give individuals and teams 4x or more productivity.  No, you
can not substitute the ingredients.  Not until you understand what they are and how they work together.  Yes, <em>I</em>
can substitute ingredients for the above, but the above are the current gold standard.  And hosting your own 'Git' is
not equivalent to using 'GitHub.com'.</p>

<h3>Four Ingredients, Three Roles</h3>

<p><img width="432" height="414" src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/add-1/ADD_FourIngredients_ThreeRoles_mlf1a1.png" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being a git about everything (IT Automation [2])]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/git-about-everything-it-automation-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-19T18:16:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/git-about-everything-it-automation-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the fifth in a series of using git as part of interesting solutions to problems.</p>

<p>The first is here: <a href="/blog/git-about-everything-intro/">Intro</a> and the previous
part of this topic is here: <a href="/blog/git-about-everything-it-automation/">IT Automation</a></p>

<h2>PushMePullYou or Leveraging git to enable mass-automated IT</h2>

<div style="float:right">
<img width="244" height="191" src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/git-about-everything-it-automation/Pushmepullyou_mlf1c.png" />
</div>


<p>The previous post dealt with the groundwork of having Git be a central part of IT automation.  That
showed the core idea but was a bit too simple to fully express the power of the approach.
This post will be dealing with all the things that were left off, especially support for:</p>

<ul>
<li> Many different types of servers with both their own and shared 'recipes'</li>
<li> More complicated install/upgrade actions</li>
<li> More sophisticated install behavior</li>
<li> Multiple versions of 'recipes' and an ability to promote whole IT from development to production</li>
<li> Getting information from other active repositories</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>To just jump-in and not be so incremental, I want to build the following deployment:</p>

<ul>
<li> A load-balancing layer that registers itself with the outside world and knows how to talk to the application layer</li>
<li> An application layer that runs an application which may be updated at any time</li>
<li> A database layer using a cluster of Riak servers</li>
<li> A presence server that can record what servers are present (so other servers can leverage)</li>
</ul>


<p>Each of these will be a different stack for easier management.  There will also be a Control server
which makes setting up the deployment easier (for example, it will make sure you have the latest AWS CLI).</p>

<h2>The Control Server</h2>

<p>To get everything up and running check out the repository:</p>

<p><code>bash
git clone git://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo4.git
</code></p>

<p>And then in the Amazon AWS console launch the control server with the file template at <code>it/aws/cloudformation/GitEvery4ControlServer.template</code>.</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/git-about-everything-it-automation-2/create_control_stack.png" /></p>

<p>You can then SSH into the server and <code>sudo su -</code> to change to root. And <code>cd gitrepo/giteveryrepo4</code> to get into the root of the repository.</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/git-about-everything-it-automation-2/control_server_login.png" /></p>

<h2>Handling Different Types of Servers</h2>

<p>A major difference from the previous example is there are now several types of servers, and they
will have different:</p>

<ul>
<li> Firewall permissions</li>
<li> Initial setup of software</li>
<li> Ongoing configuration changes</li>
</ul>


<p>There are also a number of similarities and ideally the CloudFormation files are as similar and
simple as possible.</p>

<h3>Firewall Permissions</h3>

<p>One major change is to get rid of stack-generated security groups: these are difficult to manage since
they have ever-changing and obscure names.  I believe it is better for any real deployment to control
the security groups independently of the Stacks.  So now we have two kinds of security groups:</p>

<ul>
<li> One for the <code>deployment</code> as a whole</li>
<li> One for each <code>part</code> a server node can be</li>
</ul>


<p>The <code>deployment</code> and <code>part</code> are assigned as constants in the Stack template mappings:</p>

<p>```json
  "Mappings" : {</p>

<pre><code>"TemplateConstant" : {
   "stacktype" : { "value" : "GitEvery4LbServer" },
   "initgitrepo" : { "value" : "giteveryrepo4" },
   "nodepart" : { "value" : "applbnode" },
   "deployment" : { "value" : "testdeployment" }
},
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>and then later referenced in the security group section:</p>

<p>```json</p>

<pre><code>    "SecurityGroups" : [ { "Fn::FindInMap" : [ "TemplateConstant", "deployment", "value" ] }, { "Fn::FindInMap" : [ "TemplateConstant", "nodepart", "value" ] } ],
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Before we create the stack, we create the appropriate groups.  For example, the <code>deployment</code> group will enable SSH into
the nodes and any node within the deployment to talk to any other node:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>===================</h1>

<h1>=== testdeployment</h1>

<h1>===================</h1>

<p>ec2-create-group testdeployment -d  testdeployment
export OWNER=<code>ec2-describe-group | grep GROUP | head -n 1 | cut -f 3</code></p>

<h1>Enable SSH In</h1>

<p>ec2-authorize testdeployment -p 22 -s 0.0.0.0/0</p>

<h1>Enable deployment to talk to itself</h1>

<p>ec2-authorize testdeployment -o testdeployment -u ${OWNER}</p>

<p>```</p>

<h3>Initial setup of software</h3>

<p>Within the CloudFormation template, we use the same approach as last time: simply checkout a git repository and call into it.  In Bash it would be:</p>

<p><code>``bash
yum -y install git
mkdir /root/gitrepo
cd /root/gitrepo
git clone git://github.com/markfussell/</code>cat /root/nodeinfo/initgitrepo.txt`.git</p>

<p>cd /root/gitrepo/<code>cat /root/nodeinfo/initgitrepo.txt</code>
include () { if [[ -f "$1" ]]; then source "$1"; else echo "Skipped missing: $1"; fi }
include bin/init/common/init.sh
```</p>

<p>which is converted to JSON (string-quoted) within the template.</p>

<p>This entering on a common <code>init.sh</code> entrypoint makes the CloudFormation stacks simpler and more general.  It is much
easier to update and push to the git repository than to update all the stacks that are using the repository.</p>

<p>The new part is now at the end of the common entrypoint: jumping into more specific initialization depending
on the properties of the node:</p>

<p><code>bash
include bin/init/part/`cat /root/nodeinfo/nodepart.txt`/init.sh
include bin/init/stacktype/`cat /root/nodeinfo/stacktype.txt`/init.sh
include bin/init/stacktype/`cat /root/nodeinfo/stacktype.txt`/part/`cat /root/nodeinfo/nodepart.txt`/init.sh
</code></p>

<p>We so far have three variations:</p>

<ul>
<li> The <code>part</code></li>
<li> The <code>stacktype</code></li>
<li> Combining both of the above.</li>
</ul>


<p>We can be as general or as specific as we want.</p>

<p>A <code>stacktype</code> is simply the name of the template (vs. the name of an instantiated stack which has to be unique).
The main advantage of <code>stacktype</code> is it allows easy separation of behavior by kind of stack and
also allows versioning if <code>stacktype</code> includes a version number.</p>

<p>A <code>part</code> is the singular role a node plays within a deployment.  I use <code>part</code> instead of <code>role</code> to avoid
conflict with Chef where a node can have many roles.  A node has exactly one <code>part</code> it plays in the deployment,
and each <code>part</code> can have any number of <code>roles</code>.  A <code>part</code> should normally be fairly universal.  In our case
the five parts are <code>applbnode</code> (The main application load balancer), <code>appnode</code> (The main app), <code>riaknode</code> (The
riak database node), <code>presencenode</code> (A server presence recording server), and <code>controlnode</code> (The main launching
control server, which isn't really part of the running deployment).</p>

<p>With just the application and load-balancing parts/nodes running along with the controlnode, we have something like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/git-about-everything-it-automation-2/pushmepullyou_lbandappawsarch.png" /></p>

<p>Each <code>part</code> has its own stack template and instance, which creates one or more nodes of that <code>part</code> type.</p>

<p>...More To Come...</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<ul>
<li> <a href="http://bitfieldconsulting.com/scaling-puppet-with-distributed-version-control">http://bitfieldconsulting.com/scaling-puppet-with-distributed-version-control</a></li>
<li> <a href="http://blog.afistfulofservers.net/post/2012/12/21/promises-lies-and-dryrun-mode/">http://blog.afistfulofservers.net/post/2012/12/21/promises-lies-and-dryrun-mode/</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Next</h2>

<p>Our next problem will be...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being a git about everything (IT Automation)]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/git-about-everything-it-automation/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-16T18:16:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/git-about-everything-it-automation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the fourth in a series of using git as part of interesting solutions to problems.</p>

<p>The first is here: <a href="/blog/git-about-everything-intro/">Intro</a></p>

<h2>Leveraging git to help enable automated IT</h2>

<p>Doing IT for computers involves installing software, configuring things, doing backups, updates, etc.
The ultimate IT is one that <em>'simply works'</em> and involves almost no human interaction
even in failure situations.  Ideally IT should be equivalent to
a macro-level program that does everything that does not require touching
a physical machine.</p>

<p>This IT-as-program has become easier and easier over the last many years with
better and more standardized operating systems, free software that does not
require annoying human interaction during installation, and virtualization on top of physical
hardware that makes provisioning and reprovisioning easier.  With cloud computing,
IT-as-program becomes almost a necessity as hundreds of virtual computers are created, updated, failed,
migrated, and decommissioned.</p>

<p>Git alone doesn't enable IT-as-program but it can be a core component in many areas.  Among these are:</p>

<ul>
<li> Easy 'Live IT' servers</li>
<li> A Push-Me-Pull-You model for continual deployment</li>
<li> Server presence</li>
</ul>


<p>Having git as a core piece of IT infrastructure enables thousands of machines to very rapidly react (within a minute or two)
without needing a heavy infrastructure.  You simply need one or two (for redundancy) git servers, of which one can be GitHub
or a similar free or inexpensive service.  Other technologies in this space have significantly more complicated servers,
are more likely to be SPOFs (Single points of failures) or bottlenecks, and are much more expensive as a service.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Easy 'Live IT' servers</h2>

<p>A 'Live IT' server is one that can automatically do new things when something about the IT world changes.  This
is not referring to how sophisticated the applications on a server are, but whether the server itself can
manage upgrades or other configuration changes to itself.  Examples are:</p>

<ul>
<li> Deploying new version of a Java war or a Rails app</li>
<li> Doing database backups and offloads</li>
<li> Offloading or deleting logs (that are harder than logrotate)</li>
<li> Reacting to simple configuration changes</li>
<li> Reacting to server presence changes</li>
</ul>


<p>There are a number of ways to do the activities listed above, from manually interacting with machines, through cron jobs,
mass 'push' model interactions (e.g. Capistrano), and finally puppetry via Chef and similar.  I have found almost all of
these to be lacking in many ways, including:</p>

<ul>
<li> Lack of documented change-to-server</li>
<li> Difficulty in rolling back changes</li>
<li> Not scaling nicely (one client hitting many servers, or many servers doing queries against another server)</li>
<li> Lack of flexibility</li>
<li> Slowness or non-responsiveness (delays) of applying changes</li>
<li> Differences from 'bootstrap' of cloud servers</li>
</ul>


<h3>Pull Model</h3>

<p>A different approach leveraging Git (or any other DVCS) seems to produce much simpler and more powerful
solutions.  The approach is composed of:</p>

<ul>
<li> A git repository that has working scripts (in any language people like, including Chef-solo)</li>
<li> A simple bootstrap script that clones the repository and calls an <code>init.sh</code> script in it</li>
<li> A cron job that is set up by the <code>init.sh</code> script.  This cron job executes every minute

<ul>
<li>Goes into the working git repository</li>
<li>Does a pull to get the latest version of scripts</li>
<li>Then calls into a <code>work.sh</code> script</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>This flow enables activity at every minute, using the latest version of the git repository, and with very little overhead
for the core behavior.  Advantages are:</p>

<ul>
<li> All changes to a server are caused by one or more git repositories changing.  Servers can even publish there status by showing the git revision they are on.</li>
<li> Rolling back changes is simply reversing a commit</li>
<li> The only centralized activity is the <code>git fetch</code> which is very simple and fast.</li>
<li> So far the only constraint is the time is every minute, and that could be sub-minute but needing that is rare</li>
<li> Delays are at most a minute, and again that could easily become less (but not sub-second)</li>
<li> The behavior is actually the same as bootstrapping a server.  A bootstrap is just the first minute of work.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Example-1</h3>

<p>Example-1 is the initial example of this model.  The repository is</p>

<ul>
<li> <a href="https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo3/">https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo3/</a></li>
</ul>


<p>with the CloudFormation template being:</p>

<ul>
<li> <a href="https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo3/blob/master/it/aws/cloudformation/GitEverythingServer3.template">https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo3/blob/master/it/aws/cloudformation/GitEverythingServer3.template</a></li>
</ul>


<p>This has a UserData section which does the initial bootstrap of cloning the repository and
calling an init script inside it.</p>

<p>```json</p>

<pre><code>      "yum -y install git \n",
      "mkdir /root/gitrepo \n",
      "cd /root/gitrepo \n",
      "git clone git://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo3.git  \n",

      "cd /root/gitrepo/giteveryrepo3 \n",
      "source bin/init/common/init.sh \n",
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The <code>init.sh</code> script simply sets up a cron job that calls the <code>cron_1m.sh</code> script
in <code>/root/bin/</code>.  I prefer to have crontab files that are very simple (e.g. one line)
and call into /root/bin/ scripts so (a) it is more visible what crons are running
(b) if there are any inter-cron issues they can be managed, and (c) it is easy to
disable a cron by doing a rename.</p>

<p>The <code>init.sh</code> file:</p>

<h1>```bash</h1>

<h1>=== Have a preference that crons</h1>

<h1>=== all go through a single file</h1>

<h1>================================</h1>

<p>mkdir -p /root/bin
cp ./bin/init/common/cron_1m.sh /root/bin/cron_1m.sh
chmod +x /root/bin/cron_1m.sh</p>

<p>cat &lt;<EOS > /var/spool/cron/root
MAILTO=""</p>

<ul>
<li><ul>
<li><ul>
<li><ul>
<li><ul>
<li>/root/bin/cron_1m.sh
EOS</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>```</p>

<p>And the <code>cron_1m.sh</code> file:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>! /bin/bash</h1>

<h1>================================</h1>

<h1>=== Simple worker example</h1>

<h1>================================</h1>

<p>export ME=<code>basename $0</code>
export LOG=/root/log/${ME}<em>log.txt
export ERROR=/root/log/${ME}</em>error.txt
export START_TSS="<code>date +%Y%m%d-%H%M%S</code>"</p>

<p>mkdir -p /root/log/</p>

<p>exec 1>> ${LOG}
exec 2>> ${ERROR}</p>

<p>echo "${ME}: Start  ${START_TSS}" >> ${LOG}</p>

<p>export REPOS=<code>find /root/gitrepo/ -maxdepth 1 -mindepth 1</code>
for REPO in ${REPOS}; do</p>

<pre><code>pushd ${REPO}
    git pull

    source bin/work/common/work.sh
popd
</code></pre>

<p>done</p>

<p>export FINISH_TSS="<code>date +%Y%m%d-%H%M%S</code>"
echo "${ME}: Finish ${FINISH_TSS}" >> ${LOG}</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>As you can see the <code>cron_1m.sh</code> script is "repo flexible".
It will do any and all <code>work.sh</code> file it finds in the repositories under
<code>/root/gitrepo/</code>.  You might want to be more restrictive than
that (say only 'active' repos), but this at least shows the power of the
generalization.</p>

<p>If you login to the server, you will find it doing some kind of work:</p>

<p>```bash
[root@ip-10-120-174-182 ~]# tail -f /root/log/*
==> /root/log/cron_1m.sh_error.txt &lt;==</p>

<p>==> /root/log/cron_1m.sh_log.txt &lt;==
Already up-to-date.
We are doing some kind of work
~
cron_1m.sh: Finish 20130219-050202
cron_1m.sh: Start  20130219-050301
~/gitrepo/giteveryrepo3 ~
Already up-to-date.
We are doing some kind of work
~
cron_1m.sh: Finish 20130219-050301</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>As you can see, the total time to do a "Hello World" is under a second.  Very fast!</p>

<h4>Inherent overhead of approach</h4>

<p>The amount of overhead associated associated with this approach is less than a second.  The fetch itself:</p>

<p>```bash
[root@ip-10-120-174-182 giteveryrepo3]# time git fetch</p>

<p>real    0m0.087s
user    0m0.002s
sys 0m0.006s
```</p>

<p>is 87 milliseconds and the system overhead is 8 milliseconds on an m1.small (that isn't doing anything else).
With a busier server the 'real' time goes up a bit, but the system overhead is still tens of milliseconds at
most.</p>

<p>Although fetching is useful on its own, we will initially always merge as well, so let us time that:</p>

<p>```bash
[root@ip-10-120-174-182 giteveryrepo3]# time git pull
Already up-to-date.</p>

<p>real    0m0.105s
user    0m0.007s
sys 0m0.053s
```</p>

<p>Pulling requires a bit more effort to do a no-op merge but things are still in the tens of milliseconds of 'effort'
and a clock time well under a second.</p>

<h2>Push-Me-Pull-You</h2>

<div style="float:right">
<img width="244" height="191" src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/git-about-everything-it-automation/Pushmepullyou_mlf1c.png" />
</div>


<p>The previous section discussed having 'Live IT' servers that use the very-fast git pull to
get updates that the server will react to.  Updating central git repositories uses an atomic 'push'
operation, so the obvious name for this pattern of pushing changes from one place (say 'me')
to a hundred servers who are listening (let us call them 'you') is... 'Push-Me-Pull-You'...
which even has a handy mascot.</p>

<p>Some great things about the PushMePullYou were identified above:</p>

<ul>
<li> Extremely low overhead and very simple model</li>
<li> All changes to a server are caused by one or more git repositories changing.  Servers can even publish there status by showing the git revision they are on.</li>
<li> Rolling back changes is simply reversing a commit</li>
<li> The only centralized activity is the <code>git fetch</code> which is very simple and fast.</li>
<li> So far the only constraint is the time is every minute, and that could be sub-minute but needing that is rare</li>
<li> Delays are at most a minute, and again that could easily become less (but not sub-second)</li>
<li> The behavior is actually the same as bootstrapping a server.  A bootstrap is just the first minute of work.</li>
</ul>


<p>A few additional ones are:</p>

<ul>
<li> You can 'push' from anywhere you want... so you can test a change on the target IT environment and then push from there if it works</li>
<li> It is very easy to organize many different kinds of machines, kinds of deployments, etc. within a single repository</li>
<li> It is very easy to detect whether a change happens at all, whether it is potentially relevant, and with a few easy patterns, whether it would have an impact that requires real action</li>
</ul>


<p>The architectural model looks a bit like this</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/git-about-everything-it-automation/pushmepullyou_simpleawsarch.png" /></p>

<h3>Going beyond naive</h3>

<p>The Example-1 above had the naive 'pull and do something no matter what'.  We need to get a bit beyond that
to have a truly useful approach.</p>

<h3>Checking commit version</h3>

<p>The simplest sanity check is to see whether we have a new commit.  This can be done in a few ways, including:</p>

<ul>
<li> Do a 'fetch' and check whether the remote branch is different from the local branch</li>
<li> After each action, store the commit version that was acted upon.  On each pull compare the old to the new</li>
<li> Have a local acted-upon branch separate from the main branch</li>
</ul>


<p>The last one has a nice feature of showing 'history-according-to-this-machine' where the other two are purely
'what is now', but it is simpler to avoid having a per-machine branch and multiple versions (the differing
merges depending on local history) occurring
everywhere.</p>

<h4>Fetch based</h4>

<p>The simplest check is just to see if there are any differences between the 'origin' and the local branch.  This
would look something like <code>detectOriginFetchDiff.sh</code>:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<h1>=== Detect whether the version of the origin</h1>

<h1>=== is the same as the local version.</h1>

<h1>=== Return the ORIGIN_VERSION if different</h1>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<p>git fetch</p>

<p>export ORIGIN_VERSION=<code>git rev-parse origin/master</code>
export LOCAL_VERSION=<code>git rev-parse HEAD</code></p>

<p>if [ "${ORIGIN_VERSION}" = "${LOCAL_VERSION}" ]; then</p>

<pre><code>: #Don't do anything
</code></pre>

<p>else</p>

<pre><code>echo ${ORIGIN_VERSION}
</code></pre>

<p>fi
```</p>

<p>Where you can use this script with:</p>

<p><code>bash
if [[ -n "`./bin/pushmepullyou/detectOriginDiff.sh`" ]] ; then
   : #React to the change
else
   : #Do nothing / exit
fi
</code></p>

<p>This should be lightning fast.  The only drawback is:</p>

<ul>
<li> If you don't pull (merge) until after executing the script... you might not be able to easily change the code determining whether to executing the script</li>
</ul>


<p>You can redo an action by forcing the local branch back a version.  For example:</p>

<p><code>bash
git reset --hard master~1
</code></p>

<h4>Last-action based</h4>

<p>An alternative to the fetch-based model is to record the last action performed by the local machine.  This
deals with the drawback above: you already have the latest version of code no matter what.  Also it starts
down the path of 'mid-action' protection (to avoid doing a change or sequence of changes on top of each
other).  For example <code>detectLastActionDiff.sh</code>:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<h1>=== Detect whether the last action version</h1>

<h1>=== is the same as the current pulled version.</h1>

<h1>=== Return the LOCAL_VERSION if different</h1>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<p>export LOCAL_VERSION=<code>git rev-parse HEAD</code>
export LASTACTION_FILE=./.temp/nodeinfo/lastaction.txt</p>

<p>if [[ -e ${LASTACTION_FILE} ]]; then</p>

<pre><code>export LAST_ACTION=`cat ${LASTACTION_FILE}`
if [ "${LAST_ACTION}" = "${LOCAL_VERSION}" ]; then
    : #Don't do anything
else
    echo ${LOCAL_VERSION}
fi
</code></pre>

<p>else</p>

<pre><code>echo ${LOCAL_VERSION}
</code></pre>

<p>fi
```</p>

<p>And after completing any action you write the version into the lastaction version file:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<p>export LOCAL_VERSION=<code>git rev-parse HEAD</code>
export LASTACTION_FILE=./.temp/nodeinfo/lastaction.txt
export LASTACTION_DIR="$( cd -P "$( dirname "${LASTACTION_FILE}" )" &amp;&amp; pwd )/"</p>

<p>mkdir -p LASTACTION_DIR
echo ${LOCAL_VERSION} > ${LASTACTION_FILE}
```</p>

<h3>Avoiding mid-action collision</h3>

<p>The main advantage of the Last-action approach is it starts down the path of
making sure you are not executing things twice.  Alternatively, you could
have an <code>flock</code> associated with the calling script (say the <code>cron_1m.sh</code>),
but writing to a <code>currentaction</code> file is a bit more
OS independent, can document what version is being acted upon,
and supports multiple paths hitting the same file.</p>

<p>Ideally if anything is currently working, the automatic <code>merge</code> would stop,
so the test for <code>currentaction</code> should be very early.  We should go
back to our initial worker example</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>! /bin/bash</h1>

<h1>================================</h1>

<h1>=== Simple worker example</h1>

<h1>================================</h1>

<p>export ME=<code>basename $0</code>
export LOG=/root/log/${ME}<em>log.txt
export ERROR=/root/log/${ME}</em>error.txt
export START_TSS="<code>date +%Y%m%d-%H%M%S</code>"</p>

<p>export CURRENTACTION_FILE=./.temp/nodeinfo/currentaction.txt</p>

<p>mkdir -p /root/log/</p>

<p>exec 1>> ${LOG}
exec 2>> ${ERROR}</p>

<p>echo "${ME}: Start  ${START_TSS}" >> ${LOG}</p>

<p>export REPOS=<code>find /root/gitrepo/ -maxdepth 1 -mindepth 1</code>
for REPO in ${REPOS}; do</p>

<pre><code>pushd ${REPO}
    if [[ -e ${CURRENTACTION_FILE} ]]; then
        : #Don't do anything until the current action completes
    else
        git pull

        bash bin/work/common/work.sh
    fi
popd
</code></pre>

<p>done</p>

<p>export FINISH_TSS="<code>date +%Y%m%d-%H%M%S</code>"
echo "${ME}: Finish ${FINISH_TSS}" >> ${LOG}</p>

<p>```</p>

<blockquote><p>Note: If you want to have each repository have more control of it's behavior
you would need to move the <code>if</code> test and the <code>pull</code> into the work file.</p></blockquote>

<p>While the action is running you can either touch or copy
the current version into <code>currentaction</code>, and when
finished, delete or rename it.  Since everything
is running so fast, you probably don't need to do
an <code>flock</code> or even a second <code>[[ -e ]]</code> check.  Acquiring
the lock is simply:</p>

<p><code>``bash
export LOCAL_VERSION=</code>git rev-parse HEAD`
export CURRENTACTION_FILE=./.temp/nodeinfo/currentaction.txt
export CURRENTACTION_DIR="$( cd -P "$( dirname "${CURRENTACTION_FILE}" )" &amp;&amp; pwd )/"</p>

<p>mkdir -p CURRENTACTION_DIR
echo ${LOCAL_VERSION} > ${CURRENTACTION_FILE}</p>

<h1>Now officially own the current action</h1>

<p>```</p>

<h3>Dealing with different types and collections of servers</h3>

<p>All the above had a single type of machine watching any changes in the
repository and doing the same thing.  Although this does work if you
have either very few servers or are happy with a plethora of repositories
or branches, it would be good to have a way for many different types
and collections of servers to share a single repository.  We
will deal with that in the next blog.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Git can help automate IT with a very fast and effective PushMePullYou
model.  Hundreds of servers can be continually polling one or more
central Git servers to see if anything has changed and then act
upon those changes.  This provides history for any activity, a
very fast response time, and almost no load when nothing has changed.
Also, this approach enables bootstrapping and updating to use exactly
the same paths.</p>

<p>In all, it provides a superior foundation for IT automation in spite of
being so simple.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<ul>
<li> Chef-Server Scalability

<ul>
<li><a href="http://lists.opscode.com/sympa/arc/chef/2012-01/msg00422.html">http://lists.opscode.com/sympa/arc/chef/2012-01/msg00422.html</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.opscode.com/hosted-chef/">http://www.opscode.com/hosted-chef/</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Credit</h2>

<ul>
<li> Initial Llama for Push-Me-Pull-You Image credit: <a href='http://www.123rf.com/photo_11398752_llama-llove--two-llamas-kiss-their-necks-forming-a-heart-shape.html'>fiftyfootelvis / 123RF Stock Photo</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Next</h2>

<p>Our next problem will be <a href="/blog/git-about-everything-it-automation-2/">Mass IT Automation</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being a git about everything (IT)]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/git-about-everything-it/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-13T18:16:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/git-about-everything-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the third in a series of using git as part of interesting solutions to problems.</p>

<p>The first is here: <a href="/blog/git-about-everything-intro/">Intro</a></p>

<h2>Leveraging git to help with IT tasks</h2>

<p>Doing IT for computers involves installing software, configuring things, doing backups, updates, etc.
Git can help out with a lot of this, with several big benefits.  Some examples:</p>

<ul>
<li> IT changes should always be version controlled in case of mistake.  Git and a couple patterns/tools makes that easy</li>
<li> Installing software can frequently be done with 'yum' and similar commands, but some software needs a package, and some times you want more direct 'this version' control.  An annexed git repository helps with that</li>
<li> Doing backups or other kinds of off-lining with an annexed repo is very simple and flexible</li>
<li> Git enables a PushMePullYou model that is very flexible and capable of driving hundreds of machines to do either (or both) very light and very heavy-weight operation</li>
</ul>


<p>Some of these things can be done with other tools, but I have found an annexed git repository to make doing these things easier and better</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>IT Changes</h2>

<p>Any time you have a running computer you should be careful about making changes to it that you can't
easily revert.  The classic <code>rm -fr /</code> is amongst the most painful, but even a few simple tweaks of a
configuration file could cause you minutes or hours of pain if you do them wrong and can't just
start over.</p>

<p>There are many solutions to this problem:</p>

<ul>
<li> Create a '.bak' file</li>
<li> Create a '.datestamp' file of the file before you touch it</li>
<li> Copy the file into a backup folder</li>
<li> Rsync the directory somewhere else</li>
<li> Version control the whole directory structure</li>
<li> Have frequent backups of the whole machine</li>
</ul>


<p>Git can help with a number of different approaches, but
I will start with one approach that I find to be among the simplest, most-general, and most-beneficial.</p>

<h3>Copy 'changing' files into an IT repo</h3>

<p>To get a huge step up on the problem, we are going to allocate an annexed git repository to 'being for IT'.
And further we will have every computer out there have its own directory within the repository.  A computer's
directory is simply it's name (e.g. <code>hostname</code> in unix systems).  This give us a structure like this:</p>

<ul>
<li> IT-Repository (e.g. giteveryrepo2)

<ul>
<li>it/comp/

<ul>
<li>{computer1}

<ul>
<li>Any files you want with their full path as if under '/'</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>{computer2}</li>
<li>{computer3}</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>As long as computers have unique names, we can freely work with any computer's files without collision
with another computer.  And because Git is distributed, we can work on files <em>on</em> any computer and
merging is very unlikely to be an issue.</p>

<p>An example of an IT repository is at:</p>

<ul>
<li> <a href="https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo2">https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo2</a></li>
</ul>


<p>and more specifically, the directory for computers is at:</p>

<ul>
<li> <a href="https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo2/tree/master/it/comp">https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo2/tree/master/it/comp</a></li>
</ul>


<p>As of this writing, there are two computers listed.  Both are EC2 machines, so they have the standard
patterns for AWS machine naming.</p>

<ul>
<li> domu-12-31-39-0e-e2-53</li>
<li> ip-10-28-81-39</li>
</ul>


<p>On each machine, I ran a script to copy from system files to the repository.  The scripts are in repo2/bin/copy
so a sequence looks like this</p>

<p><code>bash
./bin/copy/copyFromSystemFile.sh /var/www/html/index.html
git pull; git add it; git commit -m "Server2"; git push
</code></p>

<p>Again, because the machines have their own directories, merging should be automatic no matter what order
or how much time-overlap occurs.  Two notes:</p>

<ul>
<li> The machine names are lower-cased to avoid confusing behavior.  I strongly recommend keeping directories all lowercase</li>
<li> If you have any binary files you are copying from the machine, you need to remember to 'deflateAll' the repository before the git line.</li>
</ul>


<h4>Flattening Computers next to each other</h4>

<p>An advantage of flattening out computers next to each other is you can compare them:</p>

<p>```bash
diff -r it/comp/*
diff -r it/comp/domu-12-31-39-0e-e2-53/var/www/html/index.html it/comp/ip-10-28-81-39/var/www/html/index.html
1c1</p>

<h2>&lt; domU-12-31-39-0E-E2-53</h2>

<blockquote><p>ip-10-28-81-39
```</p></blockquote>

<p>In this case it should be apparent that the files have the <code>hostname</code> inside them, so that is what is changing.</p>

<p>So you can compare the history of a particular computer by looking through git history, and you can compare two
different computers to each other by comparing the different directories that each computer owns.</p>

<h3>Copy files from the IT repo</h3>

<p>There is also a script to copy from the IT repo to a particular system location.  This is a little more
risky, but can be useful at times.  Effectively this would roll back your local change if you didn't touch
the repo from anywhere else, and it can be used to document a proposed change before applying it.  This
leads to more of 'git for IT automation' though, which I will cover later.</p>

<h2>Software installation</h2>

<p>Software installation is the major part of machine provisioning.  Unless you have a fully-baked AMI or
really are happy with the factory install, you need to add more software to make your computer useful.
Installing software can frequently be done with 'yum' and similar commands, but some software needs a
package install (e.g. with 'rpm') and some times you want more direct control of the version installed.</p>

<p>Fetching RPMs from the web at install time is a major source of automation failure and annoyance.  Sites
go down and if you are fetching from many different sites, you could have a computer with 9 out of 10
things installed on it.  Generally I try to make machine provisioning <em>all or nothing</em> : Either everything
gets installed properly or I just wipe the machine and try again.  Primordial scripted installs are
easy to write (no human interaction), but trying to recover from a partial install is
a way to become very unproductive (potentially very angry too).  Additionally, some sites can be slow
and you don't want to be penalized by that for every computer you provision.</p>

<p>A solution is to store RPMs and the like in an Annexed Git repository.  S3 is both very fast and very reliable,
with an SLA that 'guarantees' four nines (99.99%) of uptime a year, which is &lt; 1-hour of downtime.  If
all install packages are stored in S3, provisioning would be almost solely dependent on S3, so it would
always be an <em>all (99.99%) or nothing (00.01%)</em> provisioning model.</p>

<h3>Example and idioms</h3>

<p>You could put RPMs and the like anywhere you want since the annexing is orthogonal to file location,
but I conventionally put things in 'it/resource'</p>

<ul>
<li> <a href="https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo2/tree/master/it/resource">https://github.com/markfussell/giteveryrepo2/tree/master/it/resource</a></li>
</ul>


<p>An annexed repo will also tend to have a '.temp' directory in the '.gitignore', so that is a handy place
to do temporary work without risk of colliding with changes to the repository itself.  When you inflate a file,
it is 'dirty' / changed so it could conflict with a subsequent merge and you would have to either deflate
or 'git checkout' the file/s to clean up.  Worse would be an archive that expanded into a directory structure,
so it is generally nice to work in '.temp' where these aspects don't cause issues.</p>

<p>In giteveryrepo2 there is a Java-7 rpm, which can be installed as follows:</p>

<p><code>bash
pushd /root/gitrepo/giteveryrepo2
git pull
mkdir -p .temp
cp it/resource/jdk-7u13-linux-x64.rpm .temp
./bin/inflatePaths.sh .temp/
rpm -i .temp/jdk-7u13-linux-x64.rpm
/usr/java/default/bin/java -version
</code></p>

<p>Similarly for installing Apache Tomcat:</p>

<p>```bash
pushd /root/gitrepo/giteveryrepo2
git pull
mkdir -p .temp</p>

<p>cp it/resource/apache-tomcat-7.0.35.tar.gz .temp
./bin/inflatePaths.sh .temp/</p>

<p>pushd .temp
tar -xvf apache-tomcat-7.0.35.tar.gz
mv apache-tomcat-7.0.35 /usr/share
ln -s /usr/share/apache-tomcat-7.0.35 /usr/share/tomcat7</p>

<p>popd
```</p>

<p>And just to show the install actually works.</p>

<p>```bash
cat > /etc/httpd/conf.d/proxy_ajp.conf &lt;&lt;EOS
ProxyPass /tomcat/ ajp://localhost:8009/
EOS</p>

<p>service httpd restart</p>

<p>/usr/share/tomcat7/bin/startup.sh</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>should bring up a standard Tomcat welcome screen.</p>

<p><img width="743" height="352" src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/git-about-everything-it/TomcatScreenshot1.png" /></p>

<h2>Backups</h2>

<p>Backing up database dumps, logs, etc. is as easy as copying them into an appropriate folder within the repo and deflating.
This is similar to IT changes: you just put things in a reasonable location on the machine and then</p>

<p><code>bash
./bin/copy/copyFromSystemFile.sh {reasonable-location}
./deflateAll.sh
git pull; git add it; git commit -m "Backup of `hostname` as of `date`"; git push
</code></p>

<p>This bascially works fine, with two minor issues:</p>

<ul>
<li> You probably want the backup repo to be different from the IT repo even though their layout would be similar.  You wouldn't want a bunch of 'backup' activity happening on something you are using for IT maintenance or even machine provisioning.  The rhythm and types of commits would be inconsistent.</li>
<li> At some point, you are going to have <em>too many backups</em> and you need to get rid of some noise.  This is 'cleaning the annex'</li>
</ul>


<h3>Cleaning the Annex</h3>

<p>By default the Annex has a copy of every 'big' file you have ever annexed in the history of the repository.  Given S3 doesn't
cost very much, this may never be an issue for you.  But if it is an issue, you need to throw out the garbage.  There
are fancier versions of this process but the simplest involves:</p>

<ul>
<li> Removing any files you no longer want to keep around from the current HEAD of git.  So if you have 1000 backups in the filesystem and want less than that, delete and commit the ones to get rid of.  Ideally this is completely automated as part of normal activities (e.g. new backups cause some older backups to be deleted)</li>
<li> Inflating the whole repository from the current Annex (Annex2a)</li>
<li> Changing the current Annex to point to a new empty Annex (Annex2b)</li>
<li> Deflating the whole repository to the new Annex (Annex2b)</li>
<li> Committing the change of Annex into git</li>
</ul>


<p>Note that at this point you have the option to delete the old annex or not.  If you leave it around you have a 'shiny new'
cleaner Annex2b which can make some things go faster, but if you ever want to go back to an old version it will work too.
Because the annex information is in the version, checking out an old version will automatically switch the annex to use
with it too.</p>

<p>The 'moveToNewAnnex.sh' script looks like this:</p>

<p>```bash
die () {</p>

<pre><code>echo &gt;&amp;2 "$@"
exit 1
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>[ "$#" -eq 1 ] || die "1 argument required, $# provided"
echo $1 | grep -E -q '<sup>s3://'</sup> || die "S3 bucket URL required, $1 provided"</p>

<p>export NEW_ANNEX="$1"</p>

<p>./bin/inflatePaths.sh .</p>

<p>echo $NEW_ANNEX > s3info/s3annex_config.txt</p>

<p>./deflateAll.sh
```</p>

<p>An example using the contents of 'giteveryrepo2':</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>Remove the temp directory since we don't want to annex it</h1>

<p>rm -fr .temp</p>

<p>./bin/moveToNewAnnex.sh s3://emenar.com/gitevery/giteveryrepo2v2/
git status
git diff s3info/s3annex_config.txt</p>

<h1>Go back to previous annex again</h1>

<p>git checkout -- s3info/s3annex_config.txt
git status
```</p>

<p>It would be 'more optimal' to go directly from S3 -> S3, but the above works well enough if you have decent bandwidth
and especially if you are within EC2.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Annexed git repositories can make certain IT activities much easier, more reliable, or more powerful (diff two machines' configurations).
The above wasn't showing IT automation, but it shows a valuable tool for IT automation as well as more manual interactions.</p>

<h2>Next</h2>

<p>Our next problem will be <a href="/blog/git-about-everything-it-automation/">IT Automation</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
