<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Scratch | Polyglot]]></title>
  <link href="http://markfussell.github.com/blog/categories/scratch/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://markfussell.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-06T18:05:18-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://markfussell.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Fussell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scratch on Flash]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.github.com/blog/2008/09/19/scratchonflash/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-19T18:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.github.com/blog/2008/09/19/scratchonflash</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The original version of this posting is on the <a href="http://scratch.mit.edu/forums/viewtopic.php?id=9982">MIT Scratch Forum</a></p>

<p>In the spirit of release early and often...</p>

<p>I have made a full bottom-to-top pass at implementing Scratch in Flash.  It can:</p>

<ul>
<li> Read a scratch project file</li>
<li> Create the project model (Stage, Sprites, Blocks, etc.)</li>
<li> Run that model (the core variable assignments, loops, etc.)</li>
<li> And do a couple of the other kinds of Sprite blocks in the 'motion' and 'looks' categories</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>It most definitely does not:</p>

<ul>
<li> Respond to mouse or key events yet (but that is trivial to finish...)</li>
<li> Do all the blocks... this is going to take work to map them all into Flash and especially the Sound area could be problematic</li>
<li> Draw things properly -- for one, the center of the stage is not 0,0 and the y axis is 'upside-down' [I said this was 'early']</li>
<li> Run the model correctly for all control blocks.  The core concepts are there and the blocks I have tested work right [and I picked interesting ones], but I have not tested beyond a couple projects</li>
<li> Read the Sound media at all</li>
<li> Show any of the Watchers -- Either variables or lists</li>
</ul>


<p>But given those caveats and all that I have forgotten, there is a demo at Scratch on Flash</p>

<p>You put a project URL into the text area and click 'Open'.  Then click 'Go!' and if your project responds to 'Go!' things may or may not start happening :-)    Note that the URL is smart about shared projects on this site (and locates the '.sb' file automatically if you give it the project's url) but if you use a local file system URL or some other web site, you will need to have a full path to the '.sb' file.</p>

<p>The window has a console at the bottom, a textual dump of the program above that, and has a 'Step Processor' above that.  By default the program is running one step every 30th of a second, but you can turn that off or make more steps occur every 30th of a second.</p>

<p>=======================</p>

<p>It could easily be that only the one project 'Tower of Hanoi' does anything interesting... probably within a short time some other projects would work too.  By default, I would probably start picking and choosing among Tutorials or the included 'Projects' (is there a Gallery on the site for all the Included projects?).</p>

<p>I will release source in some format in the next release -- things are pretty clean and somewhat commented, but I think I should get a little further and make sure I am not going to rename or repackage anything.  And I will need to strip out the few 'Flex' references from within the core Scratch model so a smaller SWF download is possible.</p>

<p>If anyone is interested in working on this -- doing Blocks and verifying that functionality is working, please let me know.  If people are interested then I will put source into a public RCS like Subversion or Git sooner than later.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
