<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Git | Polyglot]]></title>
  <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/categories/git/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-30T13:14:53-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Fussell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advanced Development and Delivery (ADD) and the ADD Stack – Summary]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/add2-1/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-23T01:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/add2-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the third series describing the ADD: a radically more productive development and delivery environment.  The
first series starts here: <a href="/blog/add-1/">Advanced Development and Delivery</a> and described the core four ingredients
 of the ADD.  The second series starts here: <a href="/blog/addstack-1/">ADD Stack</a> and described the application stack and
 system components associated with the ADD.  Some of these were Java / Grails specific, and some were more general
 components and capabilities.  Together these went through a huge amount of functionality, flexibility, reliability,
 and scalability.  Both for the IT infrastructure (whether on EC2 or on bare hardware) and for the applications
 on top of that IT infrastructure.</p>

<p>This series assumes you have at least skimmed the other two series, but this one is the summary of the other two.
It is an incremental growth of the architecture in a fairly macro sense, where the details are in the other series.</p>

<h2>The three ingredients</h2>

<p>Wait, it was four a moment ago.  The ADD requires four, but advanced project collaboration requires only three.  And
at the heart of the ADD is advanced project collaboration.  Collaboration has no 'machines', just people, so we put aside
one ingredient.  The remaining three are the <em>nucleus</em> of ADD:</p>

<ul>
<li>GitHub.com <a href="http://github.com/">http://github.com/</a></li>
<li>HipChat    <a href="http://HipChat.com/">http://HipChat.com/</a></li>
<li>Amazon S3  <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/">http://aws.amazon.com/</a></li>
</ul>


<p>These three ingredients can give individuals and teams 4x or more productivity.  And the reason is the same as for
 ADD.  There are two critical roles in any project:</p>

<ul>
<li>Changers</li>
<li>Watchers</li>
</ul>


<p>The Changers are gonna change, change, change, change and the Watchers are gonna watch, watch, watch, watch.  And
all of the people involve need to see what is going on (in the best way for them) and not be blocked getting things
done by others on the project.  They need perfect transparency.  Which will ultimately build incredible trust,
knowledge, and skill.</p>

<p>The three ingredients form the core of a three-way Venn diagram, that I will draw in hexagonal rings.</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/add2-1/add2_threeIngredients1.png" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Clearly the three make sense with project collaboration, and all three are used by Changers and Watchers.<br/>
Note that 'Annexes' are part of the collaboration nucleus.  You need annexed repositories for GitHub to be a practical collaboration
tool as resources become large.</p>

<h3>The fourth ingredient and full ADD nucleus</h3>

<p>Now adding the machines in, we get:</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/add2-1/add2_fourthIngredient1.png" /></p>

<p>And seeing the transformation from the three-ingredient version, we can see the EC2 servers are
not critical for Changers and Watchers to interact with each other.  Except in the sense that any final product
is part of the nucleus that Changers and Watchers want to work on.  For ADD it is a deployed application which
might be on an EC2 server, and for other product development (books, cars, etc.) it would be that <em>product</em> vs.
whatever "<em>factory</em>" created the product.</p>

<h2>The Rings</h2>

<p>So the ADD works outward from the inner collaboration nucleus plus 'the machines'.  In the other series, the tools and
system components built out more and more functionality.  They were not described this way at the time, but
they could be viewed as rings around rings.  As the rings worked outward, a specific ADD was defined
(e.g. one that was Linux and Java oriented) or a specific application architecture was defined
(e.g. on that had workers and relational databases).  All the rings are "good rings" in my experience, but
especially as you get further out each ring could be swapped with an alternative 'implementation' that
 may be more familiar to the team or somewhat more suited to the domain.</p>

<p>The rings I recommend (and recommended in the series) follow.</p>

<h3>Ring-1: Interacting with the Nucleus; EC2, Linux-capable workstations, Web Browsers, Email, and Talking</h3>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/add2-1/add2_ring1.png" /></p>

<p>In the bottom right for the machines, I recommend using EC2 as by-far the most mature and capable cloud computing
environment.  Once you are familiar with EC2, you can compare to other clouds (Google, IBM, EMC, etc.) but you
need to see a 'Real Cloud' before you can evaluate whether another is good enough.  And again, althoug I recommend
EC2, very little in the ADD is EC2-specific and it is always in the little details.</p>

<p>Having Linux-capable workstations provides the best Git, automation, and EC2 tools.  You can be on Windows, but
you will be punished.  Even worse when Ring-2 recommends Linux-Servers.</p>

<p>GitHub works fine for reading with Web Browsers, and you can even do updates with it.  HipChat is the same: it
  has an application, but it is not required.  And although most collaborative activities should be in HipChat,
  getting email notifications are quite effective.  Finally, like other Agile methodologies, direct 'talking'
  is fine and encouraged, but you need to make sure anything important gets into the collaboration environment
  (HipChat) and similarly make sure anything <em>private</em> never gets into that collaboration environment.</p>

<h3>Ring-2: The machines react and collaborate; Linux-Servers, CloudFormation, Bash, PushMePullYou, Vagrant, and HipChat notifications</h3>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/add2-1/add2_ring2b.png" /></p>

<p>Ring-2 is where the ADD starts coming truly alive and the machines 'react' to the ADD infrastructure as well as
 notify the ADD infrastructure of what is going on.  Linux-based servers (ec2 defaults to a Centos variant)
 are the most flexible, documented, and capable on the AWS (and most other) cloud infrastructures.  So this
 is an obvious choice.  Using Amazon CloudFormations is not required, but is a very simple to understand model and
 well supported in AWS.  Defaulting to using 'bash' for scripting basically makes you 'agnostic' beyond the Linux
 part.  People who don't know bash programming 'bash on bash', but it is a perfectly reasonable scripting language
 with slightly esoteric notation.</p>

<p> The PushMePullYou model is the core to mass, understandable, and fast automation.  You don't touch machines, you
 touch Git repositories, push the request (letting everyone know the request), and the machines pull it and react
 as appropriate.</p>

<p> Developers/changers can use Vagrant to run and test everything very much like production is running, including having
  their local machines come into the PushMePullYou model.</p>

<p> Finally, Git, machines, and other components should always post into HipChat so people can see what they are doing.</p>

<h3>Ring-3: An opinionated Java stack and good monitoring / logging: Grails, Spring, Maria, SumoLogic etc.</h3>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/add2-1/add2_ring3.png" /></p>

<p>Ring-3 augments the ADD into a good Java-based stack.  Both in production (a JVM running Tomcat) and
 for development (IntelliJ with a Grails/Spring stack).  By this ring we can develop software, deploy
 it, and monitor whether it is functioning properly.</p>

<h3>Ring-4: A good UI framework and any other system components needed: Angular, Redis, etc.</h3>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/add2-1/add2_ring4.png" /></p>

<p>Ring-4 finishes off most of our application functionality.  We need to pick a UI framework beyond
 generating web pages / CSS / jQuery (those are all part of Grails) if we want functionality beyond
 the core UI from Grails / Spring.  And we can augment our application servers with any of a host of
 components / technologies (as few as possible, but better to use them then to build ourselves...
 usually).</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The ADD can be thought of as rings around a "collaboration nucleus".  The nucleus and the first
two rings define the ADD approach and it's benefits, where the subsequent rings tailor
the ADD to the characteristics of good software development and high-quality
production deployment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ADD Stack [Part-10]]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/addstack-10/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-22T01:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/addstack-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second series describing the ADD: a radically more productive development and delivery environment.  The
first article is here: <a href="/blog/addstack-1/">Intro</a> and described the truth and lies about developing software.
The second article dealt with 'Testing'.  The third dealt with the application stack (Grails and other technologies).
The fourth discussed UI alternatives.  The fifth added some major aspects to the stack: Semi-Structured Data, Templates,
and Dual or Isomorphic scripting. The sixth discussed UI frameworks in a bit more detail and ended with an Angular vs.
Ember as a core choice.  The seventh went into logging, analytics, and monitoring of the running applications and nodes.
The eighth was an overview of Federation Components like caches, queues, payment services, and the like.  The ninth
was on a highly reliable, scalable, flexibly, and ultimately very simple worker model.</p>

<h2>WAR!</h2>

<p>Continuing with the worker model, we currently have a non-production Application Server running Grails:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://fed1-app1.aws.gaps2c.com:8080">http://fed1-app1.aws.gaps2c.com:8080</a></li>
</ul>


<p>It is running grails 'interactively' and 'off-source'.  This is fast for deployment, but it is missing a few
things that people usually want in production:</p>

<ul>
<li>Well-defined artifact that has been tested and can't "just change"</li>
<li>A container environment that can provide certain resources to the application (e.g. monitoring)</li>
<li>Removal of having to understand the 'building' technology from the running technology (JVM)</li>
<li>That production has as few technologies as possible, and is normally missing 'compilers' so people can't tweak behavior</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>The last item is (IMO) a bit paranoid, and there are better ways to make sure production is stable (tripwires and
logging).  And the third is probably unrealistic for anything but trivial debugging.<br/>
But the first two are certainly reasonable wants.  A lot of people are familiar with deploying wars and deploying
wars on Tomcat and other servers.</p>

<h3>Where's the WAR?</h3>

<p>The first issue with changing from source deployment to war-based deployment is "Where is the WAR?" and
"How do I know it has changed?".  As with the other weird primary ingredient approaches, the WAR is going to
be in an annexed repository.  And you can see that it changed by simply looking at whether the 'git revision' of
the war has changed.  This approach gives incredible power and flexibility:</p>

<ul>
<li>You can have as many different versions of the application as you want.  They just each have to have their own 'folder'</li>
<li>You can easily see which deployments are using which versions</li>
<li>Changing a deployment to use a different version involves copying a 50 byte hash vs. an actual WAR file</li>
<li>Getting the real file is a super-fast call to S3</li>
<li>Bootstrapping the initial version is the same as any other version, which makes it less likely to diverge and break</li>
</ul>


<p>The WARs should be in a different repository from the source for a number of reasons, but the main one being their
rules and rythms are very different.  But the structure of the repositories can be very similar to make it easy to see
the created artifacts.  Something like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-10/addstack10_war1.png" /></p>

<p>Note that the contents of the directory could be anything.  And actually a 'trick' to making the upload much faster
is to use an exploded 'war' vs. a normal 'war'.  Why?  Because a WAR contains a bunch of jars that are all almost
 always <em>identical</em> between versions.  So although S3 has basically unlimited space, it is silly to waste it with
 a file that (although different) is 99% the same between each version.  For example, all the identical jars within this
 expanded war:</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-10/addstack10_war2.png" /></p>

<p>The trade is that you have a lot more files in the other folders.  Finally, you could do a hybrid where everything but
the lib folder is compressed.  To make the real war, your deployment process would uncompress and then re-WAR the contents.</p>

<p>The performance difference is dramatically different when working outside the EC2 grid, but is less so within that
grid.</p>

<h3>Who deploys what?  The Promotion model</h3>

<p>The deploying server needs to watch something so it can see a change that is relevant to it.  Production does not care
that there is a new QA build.  And QA may not care there is a new development build.  QA never creates its own build,
but it only cares when a development build is "Good enough to QA".  This I call the promotion model.</p>

<p>For any given application:</p>

<ul>
<li>Automated builds occur <em>all the time</em> (whenever something changes) and each gets a unique identifier (e.g. 201)</li>
<li>Each build is then promoted through however many levels of inspection you want

<ul>
<li>If it passes muster</li>
<li>If it has not been superseded by another build</li>
<li>If not, it is ignored</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>With this model, you never <em>go backward</em>, which increases productivity a lot.  And your are continuously trying to
 <em>go forward</em>, which means you have very current information about where you are.  And this also increases productivity.
 Yes, in a pinch, you could see if a build <em>between</em> last success and most current can be promoted.  But that is
 impacting productivity so it should rarely be done.</p>

<p>This also implies there is no branching.  One source.  One set of builds based on that source.  That is not required
by this approach (branch source, new set of builds), but it is strongly encouraged because it again <em>wastes no energy</em>
and it is trivial to flip to a different 'set of builds' when a branch/back-patch is required.  But the process is
very optimistic while also being very realistic (the world is where it is) and appropriately pessimistic
(you can't promote through QA until you pass the automated tests).  Because machines embody the process, you
can't subvert it without doing it <em>very conspicuously</em></p>

<p>To be promoted, you just have to be 'copied' into the right destination.  Promotions are more an 'it' than
a 'development' activity, so they are structured under the 'it' folder.  Each federation (and potentially part)
has it's own versions of things.  If you are in 'fed1' and want the 'grails-petclinic' application on your
machine, you know where to look: 'fed/fed1'.  The use of 'common' vs. 'stacktype' is mirroring the flexibility
 shown elsewhere.  You could have most deployments use 'common' and have some override it.  Or most deployments override 'common'
 but there is a default in case they don't.</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-10/addstack10_promo2.png" /></p>

<h3>Who builds and deploys?  Custom Worker vs. Chores</h3>

<p>OK, so we need to build and deploy every time a particular repository changes.  We could do that monolithicly
and have no registry of the war being built (it just magically happens), or we could do that in two parts:</p>

<ol>
<li>Detect change in repository: create chore to build war</li>
<li>Detect chore and worker do chore</li>
</ol>


<p>The advantage of the second version is we can decompose figuring out what needs to be done from doing it, and we
also have better visibility and consistency in the process.  Although I like doing things incrementally, I don't
think the increment (monolith) is notably simpler than the second, and this was meant to build on our Worker topic.</p>

<p>The critical question is actually 'who is going to write the chore'.  We don't want to have a bunch of chores
created by different workers who all recognized a change was done.  Fortunately, we already have a model for this
 with the 'chore' ownership.  We need to describe an 'event' in a way that is related to whatever has changed
 about the world, and then when trying to 'create the chore' a worker first 'creates the event'.  Once an event
 is created and 'pushed', there is no reason to create it again.</p>

<p>In this case, the event is pretty obvious to describe: a git repository went to a new version or specifically:</p>

<ul>
<li>repo3_miniature-ironman</li>
<li>551b86e42d...</li>
</ul>


<p>so if an event for that exists, don't create another one.  Since this is a simple identification, we don't need
the extra directory structure and can simply write a '.json' file into the appropriate time directory.  Note the
time should be the time of the 'event', not of when it was noticed.</p>

<p>A given event could trigger multiple chores, but in our case we just want to have the one 'build the war' chore
created.  Note that the chore could be trivial: it could result in <em>no work</em> being done except seeing if a
new WAR is needed.  Chores are rarely 'you must do this', but more 'do this if necessary'.  This alows us to
be fast in the creation of the 'chore' vs. doing a lot of analysis up front.  Since the worker pool can be
large, we don't want any given worker to block the pipeline too much.</p>

<h4>Event structure</h4>

<p>The structure of the event can be anything.  It is nice to have the JSON be declarative of what it is (an 'event')
and then have enough information to process the information.  Some human readable information is handy for debugging
and logging.</p>

<p>```json
{
  "type" : "event",
  "id" :  "repo3_miniature-ironman_551b86342d"
  "tss" : "20151022120009",
  "kind" : "repochange",
  "repochange": {</p>

<pre><code>"repo" : "repo3_miniature-ironman",
"version" : "551b86342d",
"comment" : "Just set the javaagent for Java",
"committer" : "markfussell"
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<h4>Chore structure</h4>

<p>```json
{
  "type" : "chore",
  "tss" : "20151022120009",
  "event_id" : "repo3_miniature-ironman_551b86342d"
  "event" : {</p>

<pre><code>  "kind" : "repochange",
  "repochange": {
    "repo" : "repo3_miniature-ironman",
    "version" : "551b86342d",
    "comment" : "Just set the javaagent for Java",
    "committer" : "markfussell"
 }
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<h3>Making it happen</h3>

<p>Although I mentioned before that there were 'parents', 'workers', and that application servers shouldn't do any of
this kind of work, with this very clean pipeline it is clear our single application server could easily do all of
this itself.  So just to save on IT, that will be the first version.  After that it is easy to see we could separate
the 'parent/worker' from the application server.  And although likely not necessary, we could separate the 'parent'
from the 'worker' node too.  The reason the 'parent' doesn't need to be separated is we should always have two
parents around and a simple CloudFormation can make sure that is true.  And parents don't do that much, so there
is no reason to have them be separate from workers.  With this model, all workers are also potential parents, and
there are always two workers available.</p>

<h4>Detecting the change to 'Repo3'</h4>

<p>This is actually the same script as before where we just do something different in the 'ActualWork' source:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<pre><code>   echo "Detected Change in Git Version!";

   export START_TSS="`date +%Y%m%d-%H%M%S`"
   echo "Starting ActualWork at ${START_TSS}"
   echo $GIT_VERSION &gt; ${WORK_DOING_VERSION}

   source ${MY_DIR}/work_FindEvent_Repo3_ActualWork.sh
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>So now we know we have to do the work, but we need to see if it was already done by someone else:</p>

<p><code>``bash
export FIND_EVENT=</code>find work/event -name ${EVENT_NAME} | head -1`</p>

<p>echo $FIND_EVENT</p>

<p>if [[ "" == "$FIND_EVENT" ]] ;
then</p>

<pre><code> #========================================
 #=== We are the first! Rush to add it
 #========================================
</code></pre>

<p>cat &lt;<EOS >>$EVENT_FILE
{
  "type" : "event",
  "id" :  "${EVENT_ID}"
  "tss" : "${EVENT_TSS}",
  "kind" : "repochange",
  "repochange": {</p>

<pre><code>"repo" : "${EVENT_REPO}",
"version" : "${GIT_VERSION}"
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
EOS</p>

<p>git add $EVENT_FILE
git commit -m "Creating an event for the change ${GIT_VERSION}";
git push
```</p>

<p>If this push succeeds, we are free and clear.  If not, we can try to merge (maybe some other event or chore was written)
and push again with a quick 'git pull; git push'.  We could do that "forever" or until we know we have no hope (study the
actual output of the git pull, push, or other metadata between the two branches).  For the first pass, we can just do
it once.</p>

<h4>Event poster also chore poster</h4>

<p>Since we know we detected the 'event' first, we are the owner of the event and
can now safely write out the 'chores' associated with the event.</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<p>cat &lt;<EOS >>$CHORE_FILE
{
  "type" : "chore",
  "tss" : "${EVENT_TSS}",
  "event_id" : "${EVENT_ID}",
  "kind" : "buildwar",
  "war_repo" : "${WAR_REPO}",
  "war_path" : "${WAR_PATH}",
  "event" : {</p>

<pre><code>  "kind" : "repochange",
  "repochange": {
    "repo" : "${EVENT_REPO}",
    "version" : "${GIT_VERSION}"
 }
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
EOS</p>

<p>git add $CHORE_FILE
git commit -m "Creating a chore for the event ${EVENT_ID}";
git push
```</p>

<h4>Detecting and doing the chore</h4>

<p>We went through detecting the chore before <a href="/blog/addstack-9/">AddStack-9</a>, but now we want to do something with the chore.</p>

<p>Given the chore is describe in JSON and what we do for the chore could be complex, we should switch to a higher
level language than 'bash'.  In this case we can go into Python as a decent scripting language:</p>

<p><code>bash
python ${COMMON}/doChore.py --source ${RANDOM_DOIT_DIR}/chore.json --gitroot ${GIT_ROOT}
</code></p>

<p>This implies a powerful chore processing script, or one that can modularly call other scripts.
As long as the script leads the creation of 'chore' types, we should be fine whether monolithic or modular.</p>

<p>The core of the routine is just to extract the necessary information from the JSON</p>

<p>```python</p>

<p>source_directory = os.path.dirname(source)
source_json = json.load(open(source))</p>

<p>chore_kind = source_json['kind']</p>

<p>if chore_kind == "buildwar":</p>

<pre><code>build_repo = source_json['event']['repochange']['repo']
build_version = source_json['event']['repochange']['version']
war_repo = source_json['war_repo']
war_path = source_json['war_path']

buildwarfromrepo_version_torepo_path(build_repo, build_version, war_repo, war_path)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>With this information we can then go to the build repository, do a simple 'grails package', and copy it to the
appropriate repo and path.</p>

<h3>Other 'chores' for this event?</h3>

<p>The event that caused the 'buildwar' chore could also cause other activities.  Each of the
 application servers could create their own 'chore' to redeploy, which would enable the 'event' and 'chore'
 repository to reflect system activity on a broader sense.  Because they are doing the chore themselves,
 it would just be a way to log the activity vs. being a way to pass it out to a bunch of workers.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The event, chore, and worker model is a very flexible, reliable, and scalable way to get stuff done.  It is
especially good at keeping throughput under control even when tasks can get onerous or 'herding' occurs.<br/>
As the backlog grows, more workers appear to keep it in control.  When the backlog shrinks the workers go
to sleep or decommission.</p>

<p>The biggest issue with the worker approach is to make sure you know the ramp rate and reliability.  Even with a
huge cloud like EC2, there can be stutters and you have to more aggressively try to get resources, or accept that
the user experience may be a bit more lagged.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ADD Stack [Part-9]]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/addstack-9/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-21T01:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/addstack-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second series describing the ADD: a radically more productive development and delivery environment.  The
first article is here: <a href="/blog/addstack-1/">Intro</a> and described the truth and lies about developing software.
The second article dealt with 'Testing'.  The third dealt with the application stack (Grails and other technologies).
The fourth discussed UI alternatives.  The fifth added some major aspects to the stack: Semi-Structured Data, Templates,
and Dual or Isomorphic scripting. The sixth discussed UI frameworks in a bit more detail and ended with an Angular vs.
Ember as a core choice.  The seventh went into logging, analytics, and monitoring of the running applications and nodes.
The eighth was an overview of Federation Components like caches, queues, payment services, and the like.</p>

<h2>Workers!</h2>

<p>Among the more interesting federation / deployment component are workers.  Workers are interesting because
they can do almost anything imaginable and they do it very efficiently.  How efficiently?  Well, the perfect
worker is at 100% when doing a task and <em>dead</em> when they have no tasks to do.  That is pretty darn efficient
because it approaches 100% and is only not 100% when we choose to not accept the 'spin up' latency of getting
 a new worker.  As the amount of work increases, our pool of workers increase, and the spin-up-latency decreases
 on a per-chore basis.  That is <em>very cool</em>: as scale goes up, efficiency <em>increases</em>.  There are a lot of places that
 is not true for computers, so it is nice when it is.</p>

<h3>Work?  Chore?</h3>

<p>So we want to have a worker model where we can add a 'chore' (a unit of work, using a term not otherwise used in
IT and CS... job, task, etc. are now ambivalent) to a queue of work-to-be-done, and have
 something do that chore.  There are a lot of ways to do this:</p>

<p> <!--more--></p>

<ol>
<li>Use BeanStalk</li>
<li>Use Kafka with a bunch of consumers</li>
<li>Use a database and launch a worker if none is available</li>
<li>Use Quartz and coordinate amongst the application servers which one is going to do the work</li>
<li>Use GitHub and launch one or more workers as needed</li>
</ol>


<p>And that is just a minor collection of simple solutions.  The first two are probably 'the best' in terms of having
a very clean model.  But they require additional infrastructure and I am trying to keep that at a minimum.  The
second is using a database as a WorkQueue.  Well, it turns out that this is actually commonly done and almost
always <em>regretted</em>.  Most databases are horrible with the characteristics of Chores and their lifecycle.  So it does
work, but not well.</p>

<p>The fourth is quite functional but not scalable.  You don't want your application servers doing <em>a lot</em> of work.
A little housekeeping is fine.  But the whole point of the Worker model is to enable as many or as few workers who each
<em>always</em> do <em>a lot</em> of work.  And then go away if no longer needed.  That isn't the lifecycle and duty of application
servers.</p>

<p>So if you haven't guessed by now, I am going to describe the fifth approach.  Use an annexed Git repository to describe
chores, their media (if any), and to provide the results (if any).  It turns out to be blazingly fast, scalable,
and flexible.  A little weird but sometimes weird really works.</p>

<h3>Chores, Parents, and Workers</h3>

<p>A lot of time, the real world can seriously inspire the computer world.  The Worker model I am about to describe
matches a 'high-speed', 'high-efficiency', parenting model.  I would guess any parent can see the similarities
and even the Nirvana of this Worker model.  It has a few major components:</p>

<ul>
<li>The World creates some Chores in a to-do list</li>
<li>The World doesn't want to do the Chores, because it has other things to do</li>
<li>So The World creates two or more adults (for redundancy) so they can do the Chores

<ul>
<li>And then The World gives responsibility to the adults to do the Chores</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The adults don't want to actually do the Chores themselves, so they produce Workers to do the Chores</li>
<li>The Workers are so awesome that they automatically <em>all</em> try to do the Chores, as quickly as possible

<ul>
<li>The adults (Parents) have worked out a system to prevent two Workers from doing the same Chore</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>If the Chores are not getting done fast enough, the Parents produce more Workers</li>
<li>If there is no more work to do, the Workers go to sleep

<ul>
<li>Waking periodically to see if there is more work</li>
<li>Or if the Chores are not getting done fast enough, the Parents wake one or more Workers</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>With this model:</p>

<ul>
<li>The World is the Application Server or something similar</li>
<li>The Parents are special Nodes (or processes on Application Server nodes) that can see the 'to-do' list</li>
<li>The Workers are special Nodes that are created as the 'to-do' list backlog gets larger</li>
</ul>


<p>You need at least two Parents at all time to make sure the To-Do list is being watched.  You don't need any
Workers until the To-Do list is sufficiently long or latent.</p>

<p>We will put the 'To-Do' chores into a specially structured, annexed, Git repository.  Because of the annexing,
resources are automatically 'deduped' and having each 'chore' be self-contained is both possible and space
efficient.  Imagine all the 'jar's needed for a java build.  Given most of these are stable between builds,
they cost nothing at all to include in a 'chore'.  Where people run fragile artifact servers (fragile because
(a) they exist as something that could fail and (b) they are rarely run redundantly) that have to handle
heavy load, the Annex puts all that load on S3... which is designed from the ground-up for loads well beyond our workers.</p>

<h4>Chore Structure</h4>

<p>The core of a Chore has to include:</p>

<ul>
<li>The identity of the chore

<ul>
<li>And an ability to 'take it on'</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What the instructions are for the chore</li>
<li>What resources you need for the chore</li>
<li>Where the results of the chore are supposed to go</li>
</ul>


<p>To make the throughput easier to see, we will organize chores by time.  So basically a queue.  We can have 'priority' within the
metadata of the chore if we want things to jump the queue.  And we can have different chore types (or IT needs) to
make sure a worker can really handle the chore. Using the 'cron_1m' model of things working on the minute, we will
put things into buckets every minute.  But workers have to look for any not-done chore and pick it up if they can.</p>

<p>An advantage of the one-minute cron is we automatically can have a nice 30-second jitter.  That plus some kind of randomization
in chore selection makes it very unlikely that workers will acquire the same chore at the same time.  But if they do, one will win due
to 'git push' timing.</p>

<h5>Identity</h5>

<p>Chores are identified by their 'producer' and a timestamp.  A 'producer' is a node plus a process id, and the timestamp can
have any precision necessary for the process to know it can't collide with itself.  Two of the banes of any identity system
is making sure identity is unique and not having a bottleneck for identity generation.  The identity proposed solves these
two main issues.  A third requirement (sometimes) is keeping identity short / consistent.  A hash of the 'phrase' is
possible if necessary, but collisions could be an issue if the phrase is too short.</p>

<h5>Instructions</h5>

<p>So we have something like "chore_ip-1-2-3-4_ps-349467_20151022-110109-123456" as a chore.  This is simply a directory with
a 'chore.json' within it where that 'chore.json' looks something like this:</p>

<p><code>json
{
  "chore_id" : "ip-1-2-3-4_ps-349467_20151022-110109-123456",
  "chore_tss" : "20151022110109",
  "producer_id" : "ip-1-2-3-4_ps-349467",
  "runner" : "bash",
  "command" : "ps -aux",
  "result" : "output.txt",
  "error" : "error.txt"
}
</code></p>

<p>Another file is in the directory initially called 'do_it.txt' which can be empty.</p>

<h5>Take on the 'chore'</h5>

<p>To take this 'chore' on, a worker adds a 'worker.json' file to the directory:</p>

<p><code>json
{
  "chore_id" :  "ip-1-2-3-4_ps-349467_20151022-110109-123456",
  "work_id" :  "ip-4-5-6-7_ps-1000_20151022-110209-123456",
  "worker_id" : "ip-4-5-6-7_ps-1000",
  "work_start_tss" : "20151022110209",
  "state" : "working",
  "work_finish_tss" : ""
}
</code></p>

<p>and renames the 'do_it.txt' to 'doing_it.txt'</p>

<p>When these changes commit and push successfully, this worker now owns the chore.  The worker can update the 'worker.json'
through the work if desired, or put files into the directory or elsewhere.  When the chore is complete, the worker
should change worker.json to a finished state, and rename the 'doing_it.txt' to 'done.txt'.  With this,
the three states are:</p>

<ul>
<li>do_it.txt</li>
<li>doing_it.txt</li>
<li>done.txt</li>
</ul>


<p>And everyone can quickly tell what the state of a chore is without worrying about the details.  Or dive into the json
and results to figure out those details.</p>

<p>Visually it would look likte this:</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-9/addstack9_chore1.png" /></p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-9/addstack9_chore2.png" /></p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-9/addstack9_chore3.png" /></p>

<p>The script to acquire a chore is a little involved because of the possibility of failure, but basically it just</p>

<ul>
<li>Finds all the 'doit.txt' files</li>
<li>Picks one at random</li>
<li>Tries to rename it and push that change

<ul>
<li>If successful, then we are in.  If not, roll-back</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><code>``bash
export RANDOM_DO_IT=</code>find work -name 'do_it.txt' | while read x; do echo "`expr $RANDOM % 1000`:$x"; done | sort -n | sed 's/[0-9]*://' | head -1`</p>

<h1>...</h1>

<p>git mv $RANDOM_DO_IT "${RANDOM_DO_IT_DIR}/doing_it.txt"</p>

<h1>...</h1>

<p>git push
PUSH_RETVAL=$?</p>

<p>if [ $PUSH_RETVAL -ne 0 ];
then</p>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<h1>=== We failed to acquire, so roll-back</h1>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<p>```</p>

<h4>Doing the work</h4>

<p>A worker should alway be able to acquire:</p>

<ul>
<li>The root of the work repository – Say "${GIT_ROOT}"</li>
<li>The root of the chore itself – Say "${CHORE_ROOT}"</li>
</ul>


<p>Where the "GIT_ROOT" can have shared scripts in its 'work/bin' or 'bin' directories, and the chore can have
individual scripts in it CHORE_ROOT/bin directory.  We also likely have 'repo2' available,
so we have access to a lot of resources (common and work specific) to leverage.</p>

<h4>Saving the work</h4>

<p>When the worker is done, it needs to do a final 'write' of all the results.  This could be nothing more than
logs (a worker is 'anonymous' and ephemeral, so ideally logs go to the chore's directory vs. somewhere
effectively 'random').  This is just a final pull-push:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<h1>=== Done, try to write out the results</h1>

<h1>===</h1>

<h1>=== Make sure everything is annexed</h1>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<p>./bin/deflatePaths.sh "${RANDOM_DO_IT_DIR}"</p>

<p>git pull</p>

<h1>...</h1>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<h1>=== Pull successful, start writing</h1>

<h1>=================================================</h1>

<p>git mv "${RANDOM_DO_IT_DIR}/doing_it.txt" "${RANDOM_DO_IT_DIR}/done.txt"</p>

<p>git add -A "${RANDOM_DO_IT_DIR}/../"
git commit -m "$ME completed chore ${RANDOM_DOIT_DIR}"</p>

<p>git push
```</p>

<p>and as long as this is successful, the work is done.</p>

<h4>Jitter</h4>

<p>Although the randomization of chore selection helps with a lot of chores, it does not help when there are very few
chores left.  On the 'go' of chore selection, all the workers go after the chore.  So we need to say 'go' at
different times.  This brings back the 'jitter' concept mentioned previously.  To jitter in this case, we just
create a 'random' number and then modulo it by whatever jitter interval we want.</p>

<p>For example, using the process id plus the time stamp, and trying for a 0-29 range, we can have:</p>

<p><code>bash
TSS_SECOND=`date +%s`
PSEUDO_RANDOM="`expr ${TSS_SECOND} + $$`"
SLEEP_LENGTH=$((${PSEUDO_RANDOM} % 30 ))
</code></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The above is a very generic worker model that enables all kinds of flexibility in setting up 'chores' and scalably
having a 'right-size' for the number of workers doing the work.  The next article will be more specific and
build new 'wars' every time the application changes after passing the built-in tests.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ADD Stack [Part-8]]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/addstack-8/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-20T01:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/addstack-8</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second series describing the ADD: a radically more productive development and delivery environment.  The
first article is here: <a href="/blog/addstack-1/">Intro</a> and described the truth and lies about developing software.
The second article dealt with 'Testing'.  The third dealt with the application stack (Grails and other technologies).
The fourth discussed UI alternatives.  The fifth added some major aspects to the stack: Semi-Structured Data, Templates,
and Dual or Isomorphic scripting. The sixth discussed UI frameworks in a bit more detail and ended with an Angular vs.
Ember as a core choice.  The seventh went into logging, analytics, and monitoring of the running applications and nodes.</p>

<h2>Federation Application Infrastructure</h2>

<p>The application stack we have so far:</p>

<ul>
<li> UI (both client and server)</li>
<li> Application Server (Grails, Java, potentially scripting engine)</li>
<li> Database (Maria or similar)</li>
</ul>


<p>Is very capable.  Using it combined with the ADD ingredients:</p>

<ul>
<li> GitHub – With resource, presence, application, and configuration information repositories</li>
<li> EC2 Instances – Running continuously or based on load, and running their 'part' plus any dynamic configuration</li>
<li> S3 – For resources</li>
<li> HipChat – To let everyone know</li>
</ul>


<p>Makes for a very functional application.  The nodes and their applications can talk to each other based on presence.
The nodes and their application can keep certain data in-memory (cached).  The nodes can
 launch other nodes to handle load or do certain tasks.  An Application Server is a very generic thing and
 can do pretty much anything.</p>

<h3>Standard Federation Components</h3>

<p>Doing pretty much anything and everything turns out to be very confusing.  For people.  Big monoliths of capabilities
are basically beyond comprehension.  And the bigger the monolith, the harder it falls.  The more likely it falls.
And even if you have redundant monoliths, the system becomes very painful to maintain and to learn.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>So instead of having the one super-capable application server, we can start breaking out some of the responsibilities
of the application server into other system components, and then decide whether we need them or not.  If we need
them, we will be using a very main-stream approach that is redundant, scalable, and easily managed.  It needs to 'fit'
with our application, but it doesn't have to be similar to the application (e.g. works with Java, written in Erlang,
runs on Linux).</p>

<p>The list of standard system components isn't that long, but it is <em>longer than you need</em>.  If you are using all of these,
you are likely over-engineering your solution.  Try to start weaning yourself off some of this technology.</p>

<p>A partial list of federation components</p>

<ul>
<li>Cache – For rapidly retrieving information that changes slowly or needs to be shared broadly</li>
<li>Queue – For getting information from producers (requests) to consumers (workers)</li>
<li>Distributed State – For precise and consistent decision-making among several different entities</li>
<li>Semistructured Database – For persistently storing data in a faster or more flexible format than the main database</li>
<li>SSO (Single Sign-on) – To enable users to get access to various resources without the resources having to authenticate</li>
<li>"Chat" – Real-time presence and data communication enabling 'chat' and various other capabilities</li>
<li>Map-Reduce – Taking large amounts of data and processing it to get answers to questions.  Can be real-time or not</li>
<li>Forum – Supporting forum capabilities for customers to talk with each other</li>
<li>Customer Support – Supporting customer-facing capabilities, including defect and product request tracking</li>
<li>SMS / Email / Contact – Ability to send out emails, SMS, surveys, and other customer contact</li>
<li>Web Site – A separate web site from the main application</li>
<li>Web Content Creator – An ability to enable users to create content within your site (vs. doing it via templating)</li>
<li>Payment Processing – Handling the record of credit cards and payment processing</li>
<li>Freetext Search – The ability to search documents and similar free text</li>
<li>Workers – Special nodes that do work and either go idle or disappear when no work is needed</li>
</ul>


<p>There are some more (e.g. the BI pipeline), but that is a pretty good list.  Especially the 'Workers' is a category basically as broad as
'Application'.</p>

<p>Working through the list, here are some examples:</p>

<ul>
<li>Cache – Redis <a href="http://redis.io">http://redis.io</a></li>
<li>Queue – Kafka <a href="http://kafka.apache.org">http://kafka.apache.org</a></li>
<li>Distributed State - Presence in Git (for minutes), ZooKeeper (for sub-second) <a href="http://zookeeper.apache.org">http://zookeeper.apache.org</a> and Curator <a href="http://curator.apache.org/curator-recipes/index.html">http://curator.apache.org/curator-recipes/index.html</a></li>
<li>Semistructured Database – Riak  <a href="http://basho.com/products/">http://basho.com/products/</a></li>
<li>SSO – Shibboleth <a href="http://shibboleth.net">http://shibboleth.net</a></li>
<li>Chat – Ejabberd <a href="https://www.ejabberd.im">https://www.ejabberd.im</a></li>
<li>Map-Reduce – Spark <a href="https://spark.apache.org">https://spark.apache.org</a>,  Hadoop <a href="https://hadoop.apache.org">https://hadoop.apache.org</a></li>
<li>Forum –  phpBB <a href="https://www.phpbb.com">https://www.phpbb.com</a></li>
<li>Customer Support – Parature <a href="http://www.parature.com">http://www.parature.com</a></li>
<li>SMS / Email / Contact – SendGrid <a href="https://sendgrid.com">https://sendgrid.com</a> , Silverpop <a href="http://www-03.ibm.com/software/products/en/silverpop-engage">http://www-03.ibm.com/software/products/en/silverpop-engage</a> , SurveyMonkey <a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com">https://www.surveymonkey.com</a> , etc.</li>
<li>Web Site –  Expression Engine <a href="https://ellislab.com/expressionengine">https://ellislab.com/expressionengine</a> , Squarespace <a href="http://www.squarespace.com">http://www.squarespace.com</a></li>
<li>Web Content Creator – How about the original 'wiki' <a href="http://wiki.org">http://wiki.org</a> or a more modern one like Foswiki <a href="http://foswiki.org">http://foswiki.org</a></li>
<li>Payment Processing – PayPal <a href="http://paypal.com">http://paypal.com</a> or even Facebook <a href="http://facebook.com">http://facebook.com</a> and Google <a href="http://google.com">http://google.com</a></li>
<li>Freetext Search – Solr <a href="http://lucene.apache.org/solr/">http://lucene.apache.org/solr/</a></li>
<li>Workers – All kinds of workers and frameworks for doing it, including AWS beanstalks <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/elasticbeanstalk/latest/dg/using-features-managing-env-tiers.html">http://docs.aws.amazon.com/elasticbeanstalk/latest/dg/using-features-managing-env-tiers.html</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Sadly, Rumble did use almost all of the above (and more) in some way or another, but that is seriously off-the-chart
and incredibly expensive.  Yes, it is powerful.  No, your users do not care to pay you for that much power.</p>

<p>A company like Wikipedia/Wikimedia looks more like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-8/addstack8_wikimedia1.png" /></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>It is good to understand what kinds of system components are out there and be aware that you don't have to
reinvent / recode them when you need them.  Each of the above are good products.  They do what they should
to fill a particular need.  And almost all of them are
fault-tolerant and scalable, so they can join the rest of the <em>very tolerant</em> ADD stack.
Or they are a service and you get what you pay for.  If you really need
one of them, certainly bring it aboard.  It is better than creating a monolith.
But if you can do without it, your application and you IT will be easier to understand and maintain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ADD Stack [Part-7]]]></title>
    <link href="http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/addstack-7/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-19T01:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://markfussell.emenar.com/blog/addstack-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second series describing the ADD: a radically more productive development and delivery environment.  The
first article is here: <a href="/blog/addstack-1/">Intro</a> and described the truth and lies about developing software.
The second article dealt with 'Testing'.  The third dealt with the application stack (Grails and other technologies).
The fourth discussed UI alternatives.  The fifth added some major aspects to the stack: Semi-Structured Data, Templates,
and Dual or Isomorphic scripting. The sixth discussed UI frameworks in a bit more detail and ended with an Angular vs.
Ember as a core choice.</p>

<h2>Logging, Analytics, and Monitoring</h2>

<p>Returning to a bit more of an 'IT' issue, how do we handle logging, monitoring, and analytics on our collection of
machines?  There are a number of choices:</p>

<ol>
<li>Run our own infrastructure</li>
<li>Go with an inexpensive provider</li>
<li>Go with a more capable provider</li>
<li>Don't</li>
</ol>


<p>Of the above, I believe #3 is usually worth it until your scale gets to the point of needing #1.  Downgrading
from #3 to #2 is fine <em>after</em> you have learned the capabilities you are giving up.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Logging: SumoLogic</h3>

<p>The longest standing, very successful, and SaaS capable company is Splunk (<a href="http://splunk.com/">http://splunk.com/</a>) .  But their prices are crazy.  Have no
idea how they can charge that much.  So instead I will demo SumoLogic (<a href="http://SumoLogic.com/">http://SumoLogic.com/</a>) as the '3B' tier.</p>

<p>Installing SumoLogic is incredibly easy:</p>

<p><code>bash
wget "https://collectors.us2.sumologic.com/rest/download/linux/64" -O SumoCollector.sh &amp;&amp; chmod +x SumoCollector.sh &amp;&amp; ./SumoCollector.sh -q -VskipDefaultSources=true -Vsumo.token_and_url={token}
</code></p>

<p>And the collector is on the machine.  If you tell it what you want to aggregate, it starts collecting and indexing files in those paths.  In our case, the nodes
all have files in '/root/log' which it would be nice to have aggregated.</p>

<p>The results are visible here:</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_sumo1.png" /></p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_sumo2.png" /></p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_sumo3.png" /></p>

<h4>Logging Alternative: Graylog</h4>

<p>For Rumble, we had a Graylog (<a href="http://graylog.com/">http://graylog.com/</a>) cluster that dealt with a tremendous amount of data (half a
terabyte a day if memory serves, due to over-enthusiastic logging) and was relatively stable under that load.
Elasticsearch had issues if a node failed (just due to the stress of moving data to another backup), but this
is under pretty extreme load levels.  So if you wanted to roll your own, the Graylog path would be a very
inexpensive and powerful path.</p>

<h3>Analytics and Monitoring: NewRelic</h3>

<p>NewRelic (<a href="http://newrelic.com/">http://newrelic.com/</a>) started out as a Ruby-oriented monitoring service, and basically came about because Ruby/Rails developers
(a) wanted a lot of information about why their apps were running slowly, (b) had very little knowledge about
operations and other ways of monitoring things, and (c) Ruby itself has little support for monitoring.  NewRelic
came along and provided the metrics (as you would expect for Java and similar mature languages) <em>outside</em> the
Ruby environment.  Initially this could be viewed as a crutch for Ruby where Java didn't need it, but ultimately
by putting the metrics outside the application everyone's life was simpler.</p>

<p>To install NewRelic, you need to get the agent onto the machine.  In our case we are going to leverage the annex:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>====================================================</h1>

<h1>=== Install NewRelic</h1>

<h1>====================================================</h1>

<h1>===================================</h1>

<h1>=== Server</h1>

<h1>===================================</h1>

<p>rpm -Uvh http://download.newrelic.com/pub/newrelic/el5/i386/newrelic-repo-5-3.noarch.rpm
yes | yum -y install newrelic-sysmond
nrsysmond-config --set license_key=key</p>

<p>/etc/init.d/newrelic-sysmond start</p>

<h1>===================================</h1>

<h1>=== Java</h1>

<h1>===================================</h1>

<p>export APP_VERSION=3.21.0
export APP_FULL_VERSION=newrelic-java-${APP_VERSION}</p>

<p>mkdir -p .temp
cp it/resource/${APP_FULL_VERSION}.zip .temp/</p>

<p>./bin/inflatePaths.sh .temp/${APP_FULL_VERSION}.zip</p>

<p>mkdir -p /opt
cp -fr .temp/newrelic /opt/</p>

<p>cp -fr ${RESOURCE}/newrelic.yml /opt/newrelic/newrelic.yml</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>The first section puts on the system-monitoring agent for newrelic.
The second section has two parts.  The first part puts the general NewRelic agent onto the machine, and the second part
enables us to override (overlay) the default configuration with our own.  The most important part is to replace the
license, but there are many things that can be configured within the NewRelic agent.</p>

<p>Finally, we need to launch with the agent configuration into the java / 'gradew' launcher:</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<h1>Add default JVM options here. You can also use JAVA_OPTS and GRADLE_OPTS to pass JVM options to this script.</h1>

<p>DEFAULT_JVM_OPTS="-javaagent:/opt/newrelic/newrelic.jar"
```</p>

<p>After doing this and waiting for the metrics to hit the NewRelic servers, we get some nice visuals:</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_newrelic2.png" />
<img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_newrelic4.png" />
<img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_newrelic5.png" />
<img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_newrelic6.png" />
<img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_newrelic7.png" />
<img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_newrelic7.png" /></p>

<h3>Operational Monitoring: Nagios and Icinga</h3>

<p>The above monitoring is not 'alert' oriented.  It lets you drill into the details of what is happening
in operations both currently and somewhat into the past.  To be a bit more alert oriented, you need
to go down a different path.  The most mature open source path is the Nagios / Icinga double path (<a href="http://nagios.org/">http://nagios.org/</a>,
 <a href="http://icinga.org/">http://icinga.org/</a>).</p>

<p>An important aspect of monitoring is to have <em>multiple</em> monitors on your network.  And, in general, for the monitors
to be outside the data center.  Agents within the data center can relay information out, but if your monitors fail
inside the data center, you are (unknowingly) blind.</p>

<p>So for Nagios, we can demonstrate monitoring from the developers (or operations dashboard) machine vs.
within the data center.  Because of the presence being visible from anywhere, monitoring configuration can happen
anywhere that you can pull out a git repository.</p>

<p>Examples of Nagios views are:</p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_nagios1.png" /></p>

<p><img src="http://markfussell.emenar.com/images/addstack-7/addstack7_nagios2.png" /></p>

<p>Where the lists of hosts to monitor and what to monitor comes from text configuration files.</p>

<p><code>
define host {
   host_name   {host_name}
   use         {node_type}
   alias       {node_id}
   address     {node_public_address}
   register    {registration_order}
}
</code></p>

<p>And these files can trivially be generated from the presence information, and updated if
anything changes.  An important aspect is to make sure to turn off the monitoring system
when a node is going down <em>intentionally</em>.  So the 'node_state' status and 'node_app_state'
status are critical to have come through the presence information for monitoring to
not be 'noisy'.  A noisy monitor is a monitor that will quickly be forever ignored.</p>

<p>Although Nagios and Icinga have dashboards, everything should go into HipChat so everyone
can see the history and stability/instability of the system.  You can even publish the status
  publicly so your users will know there is a production problem. If you enable public chat
  in either HipChat or elsewhere, the users can both see the status and ask for predictions
  of when issues are resolved.  A much higher-touch relationship with users can make them
  longer users (this retention aspect was very true of Winster where the CEO was <em>online</em>
  and could be chatted with a good portion of the evening.  Kind of like walking the floors
  of the casino or Tim Cook being in the University Apple Store.).</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Although it is more operational than "application stack", the ability to monitor and analyze your
application's performance and behavior is critical to any production deployment of it.  So you
should think about it early and not as an afterthought.  All logging should go into the logging pipeline
(no System.println or equivalent) and be searchable through that pipeline at one or more aggregators.
Start out with a metrics system like NewRelic to get a bunch  of valuable things for free
and you can later add in new application-specific metrics.
And get the basics of operational monitoring up early and you will know if the application and the
IT is reliable long before it gets into the production data center.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
